Empresses in the Palace—the Legend of Zhen Huan
Adapted from the novel by Liu Lian Zi
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
https://magpiebridgebrigade.cn
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Theme: Unfortunate Love
I can cut a thousand strands of hair
but I cannot sever the tangled threads of my mind.
Bowing with my hands clasped, I give away my throne.
Lowering my head, devoted to the beauty by my side.
The wheel of fate turns, granting blessings or misfortune.
Will it be destiny’s trial or reward?
Heaven’s will cannot be known,
weaving together weals and woes.
For lovers caught in eternal time,
who can break the spell of romance?
Bowing with my hands clasped, I give away my throne.
Lowering my head, devoted to the beauty by my side.
The wheel of fate turns, granting blessings or misfortune.
Will it be destiny’s trial or reward?
Heaven’s will cannot be known,
weaving together weals and woes.
For lovers caught in eternal time,
who can break the spell of romance?
Who can break the spell of romance?
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
https://magpiebridgebrigade.cn
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Despite their beautiful flowers,
apricots are sour
and the seeds are bitter.
Life is meaningless
if it begins well but ends badly.
I'd rather have an evergreen life like pine
and cypress, and not bloom or bear fruit.
My Lady, we should head back.
The kitchen made partridge stew with sweet and bitter apricot kernels.
It’s most nutritious this time of year.
Let’s go back.
I do feel hungry.
Your Majesty.
I humbly suggest that the case of
Qian Mingshi need not be pursued further.
Condemning poems have been written.
More may lead to everyone in court living in fear.
Who would dare to speak or write freely?
If adulation dominates the court,
it will be hard to promote righteousness.
Are you suggesting that I am suppressing criticism?
I dare not.
It’s only that as a civil official,
if I cannot perform my duty and speak freely,
then I am failing to fulfill Your Majesty’s great benevolence.
Your Majesty.
Zhen Yuandao shows no remorse
for his dissenting opinion.
He should be punished severely.
As Your Majesty observes,
Zhen Yuandao's disloyalty is obvious.
However, given that Her Highness
Concubine Souire is pregnant,
If Your Majesty wants to punish Zhen Yuandao,
it should be postponed and carried out in stages.
Your Majesty,
Zhen Yuandao is the father of Concubine Sourire.
But he should not consider himself an imperial in-law.
He should not be arrogant about Your Majesty’s
benevolence and disobey Your Majesty.
If he is exempted because his daughter is a concubine,
there will be no justice and discipline in the court.
“If an emperor breaks the law,
he is punished the same as a commoner.”
Zhen Yuandao will be suspended and imprisoned.
His family will be confined in their residence.
I ...
humbly thank Your Majesty.
Jinxi, today is Double Ninth Festival.
We should present the Empress Dowager
with gifts and our best wishes.
I asked you to prepare chrysanthemum cakes and wine.
Are they ready?
Yes. I also included a cherry dogwood
sachet tied with a red ribbon.
And I covered it with mulberry and elm
leaves to make it a three-color gift.
Madam Orchid sent it to Her Majesty early this morning.
This conveys “sunset on mulberry and elm
trees” to wish Her Majesty happiness.
Peace to Your Highness.
Why do you come in person, Madam?
Her Majesty is very delighted with your presents
and is thinking about your pregnancy.
So she sent me to deliver her greetings.
I’m thankful for Her Majesty’s consideration.
Now that Your Highness is pregnant,
the confinement must be hard for you.
If there is anything that inconveniences
Your Highness, please have Orchid tell me.
I am happy to serve Your Highness
to the best of my ability.
There is nothing important.
It’s just that today is the Double Ninth.
"I imagine my brothers climbing up to the highlands.
They would have dogwood sprigs attached and my absence noted."
It’s only ...
that I'm missing my family.
There is a rule in the harem.
When a concubine is eight months pregnant,
her family is allowed to accompany her until labor.
We’re very close to that time.
I will remind the Household Department to
arrange for Your Highness's mother to visit.
Although I offended/displeased His Majesty,
I feel reassured that my family was not implicated.
I have duties to Her Majesty, so I can’t stay long.
I will take my leave.
Thank you, Madam.
Regretfully, I can’t see you off.
Take care, Your Highness.
Her Highness didn’t suspect anything, did she?
I came with Her Majesty’s well-wishes.
I don’t think Her Highness would be suspicious.
Thanks Amitābha Buddha.
This is properly dealt with.
How could this happen all of a sudden?
When I went sent His Majesty’s Double
Ninth gifts to Her Majesty this morning,
I didn't expect Her Majesty would send
me to visit Her Highness.
I knew since early morning about the
Zhen family's incident, which unsettles me.
How could I face Her Highness myself?
So I had to trouble you, Madam.
We can hide it for the moment, but not forever.
Her Highness is due soon.
She can’t know about this.
What if her prenatal qi is affected?
That's also what I was thinking.
Fortunately, no final conviction
has been made of the Zhen family.
Perhaps His Majesty will have mercy
on account of Her Highness.
This isn’t what we should worry about.
Let’s go back.
It’s always been Madam Orchid coming here.
How come it was Madam Bamboo today?
Perhaps Her Majesty likes your gifts very much.
So she’s sent Madam Bamboo to show more respect.
Don’t you think Madam Bamboo was acting strangely?
Don’t overthink it, My Lady.
It’s time to take your prenatal tonic.
I’ll go bring it.
This Dong'e ejiao soup has been simmered for six hours.
It melts in your mouth.
Do you like it, Imperial Mother?
It’s very good, sweet and glutinous.
I'm glad you like it, Imperial Mother.
People say that sweet foods bring
happiness to your heart.
However,
I can barely taste the sweetness in the soup.
I heard an official spoken out
in favor of Zhen Yuandao.
It enraged the Emperor, and he was also
imprisoned at the Ministry of Justice.
That’s true.
The court is turbulent,
and the harem is not peaceful.
I am incapable.
It’s not that you’re incapable.
You are smarter and more capable
than Empress Première.
All these years, I have never interfered
in how you carry out the role of
a Lady and then an Empress.
But, there is one thing.
The Imperial Harem is centered on heirs.
The women in the harem are like
an endless procession of flowers.
While you take the effort to remove one,
there will be another coming in.
As the Empress, you are to manage the flowers
rather than constantly trimming them,
resulting in a bare tree.
Moreover,
you can’t under any circumstances harm the heirs.
Ever since I lost the First Prince,
I've always been hoping His Majesty
will have a desirable heir to his throne.
Although His Majesty has three sons ...
Only three sons!
How many did the prior emperor have?
Even the last digit is larger than three!
A lack of imperial heirs is the
lack of virtue of the Empress.
Go stand in front of the Cricket Gate.
And reflect on what I just said.
Yes.
Peace and grace to Your Majesty.
It's windy right now.
Your Majesty should return to your palace.
Concubine An, do you know the
meaning behind the Cricket Gate?
I do not. I hope Your Majesty
would enlighten me.
In the Classic of Poetry,
“Ye winged crickets, how you cluster together!
Right is it that your descendants - should be in swarms!”
This name for the gate wishes the
imperial family may have many heirs
to continue the imperial rule through generations.
I really wish I had a son of my own.
The First Prince was already
able to talk and laugh.
But a sudden disease ...
took away his life right from my arms.
Now I have to watch the concubines
getting pregnant one after another,
and one child born after another...
How can I endure it emotionally?
Your Majesty,
children not favored by you
don't deserve to be born to this world.
Solely because you are the "Mother of the Nation."
Likewise, women not favored by Your Majesty
shouldn't live to disgust you either.
That's why I favor you.
Your Majesty.
Concubine Sourire is already eight months pregnant
and about to give birth.
Giving birth is a good thing.
I will have one responsibility off my shoulder.
It's a pity Concubine Sourire is already
so late into her pregnancy.
If she was to learn about
what happened to her family,
who knows how saddened she would be.
The doctor must take good care of her
and no one shall let the word get out to her.
I will obey Your Majesty's order.
Your Majesty, allow me to
accompany you back to your palace.
There's no need.
His Majesty should have just
awoken from his afternoon nap.
You should go back and serve by his side.
I am thankful for Your Majesty's advice.
Go.
I'm already eight months pregnant.
Why hasn't the Household Department
arranged for my mother to visit?
When Madam Orchid visited this morning,
she was also ambiguous with her words.
The last time Su Peisheng came,
he passed the words
that I should avoid going out
for walks due to the cold weather.
My Lady, they are just thinking about your health.
Madam Orchid is a direct servant to His Majesty.
But the Household Department is
responsible for arranging your family's visit.
Madam Orchid probably has not
had the chance to ask about it yet.
For the past few days, I've been feeling disquieted.
Just look at all the eunuchs guarding my palace.
The numbers have increased many folds.
My Lady, you're about to give birth.
It's normal for them to be more cautious.
All right then.
My child will be born soon.
By then, the weather would be cold.
I want to sew some more quilts for him.
Good idea, My Lady.
Allow me to help you.
My Lady, you don't have to do any of the needlework.
Leave that to me.
All right. I will pull the cotton then.
Peace to Your Highness.
Your Highness's due date is near.
The Household Department has ordered
me to deliver the Easy Labor Stones
to protect Your Highness and your child.
What's your name?
I've never met you before.
Your Highness, my name is Xiao-Guizi
and I am new to the palace.
Mr. Huang was supposed to come today,
but he had a stomach ache and sent me instead.
My Lady would like to treat you to a cup of tea.
I thank Your Highness.
This is just a small reward.
Once my family comes to visit me,
I will reward you more.
I thank Your Highness.
But I haven't heard about
arranging any noblewomen to visit.
May I ask which distinguished family
Your Highness is from?
I do not come from a prestigious family.
Unlike the Zhen family, my mother
cannot frequent the palace.
Although the Zhen family was once prominent,
they have fallen now.
I just heard a few days ago
that Mr. Zhen was imprisoned.
Not only was he imprisoned at an old age,
but the officials that argued for
him were also implicated.
How could this happen?
Didn't the Zhen family
accomplish a great feat for quelling
Nian Gengyao and State Prince Dun?
Your Highness, they have also
committed a major crime.
The Nian family was a great example.
Someone informed against Mr. Zhen.
Who did it?
Tell us!
- It was Mr. Gūwalgiya.
- Nonsense!
Wasn't Mr. Gūwalgiya always close with Mr. Zhen?
Why would he inform against Mr. Zhen?
I wouldn't know much about the
happenings in court.
But this matter has been known to everyone.
I wouldn't dare lie about this.
I still have other tasks to attend to.
Allow... Allow me to take my leave.
My Lady, what should we do?
My Lady...
Very well... Very well...
My Lady! My Lady!
Her prenatal qi must have been affected.
Hurry! Send for Dr. Wen.
Peace to you, My Lady.
Have you done your task well?
Yes, My Lady. Just as you have ordered.
I heard they were calling for the imperial doctors.
Well done.
What happens next will be up to her own fortune.
I have another task for you.
I await your order, My Lady.
Go find something for me
and bring it directly to the prison
at the Ministry of Justice.
Sir, it's filthy inside. Please come out soon.
I don't need you telling me what to do.
Yes, Sir. Please do as you wish.
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Somebody come! There are rats in here!
Rats! There are rats!
Dr. Wen, is everything all right with My Lady?
Nothing serious.
I just have something to ask Your Highness.
I also have some questions for you, Dr. Wen.
Yes.
Your Highness, what caused you such intense pain
to even affect your prenatal qi?
Yesterday, a eunuch came to tell me
what happened to my family.
Since you can get out every day,
you must have known about it.
Has Your Highness known all about it?
Who had the audacity to tell Your Highness?
So you really know.
Even if I don't ask,
someone will find ways to let me know.
For one thing, I am entrusted by His Majesty.
For another, I have to consider
the impact on Your Highness's health.
Now that I know it,
do you still intend to keep it from me?
Mr. Zhen was deposed and put into jail.
Her Ladyship and your sister are confined at home.
They are in the same situation as Your Highness.
The same situation?
I am taken care of because I am pregnant.
Can my parents also be treated the same?
It was Gūwalgiya Emin who reported that
Mr. Zhen showed sympathy for the traitor.
Showed sympathy for the traitor?
How could he say so?
Does Your Highness remember Qian Mingshi?
Your father refused to go with the flow
and didn't write any reprehensive poems.
Then was considered by His majesty
to be sympathetic to the traitor.
Isn't that ...
a fabrication/fabricated accusation?
After experiencing the Nian Gengyao incident,
His Majesty has been vigilant against
these meritorious officials
and did not entrust them with high powers.
Only Mr. Zhen was the most valued.
But shortly after peace was restored,
such a rumor came out.
In order to clean up opposing factions,
His Majesty was very concerned about such a rumor.
So His Majesty believed it?
Every word on Gūwalgiya Emin's report
broke the taboo of His Majesty.
How could His Majesty not believe it?
“After the cunning hare is killed,
the hound is boiled.”
Not only me...
My whole family has been plotted against.
No, My Lady...
Xiao-Guizi said that
he was new to the palace.
He didn't know your family name is Zhen.
How could he know this about our family?
Do you believe he is a new comer?
His Majesty holds my palace in high regard ...
How could the Household Department
send a servant who knows nothing?
It's clear that someone wanted to
send me the words through his mouth.
If I hadn't had a strong heart,
I'm afraid I could have lost my child.
They are so vicious.
I have to see His Majesty.
But time has changed,
His Majesty may not be willing to see me.
Please hand this over to His Majesty
together with my letter.
To my beloved wife Surissé:
My heart aches when I think of your tragic passing.
Leaving me behind in this sorrowful shell.
You lift my soul to see you in my dreams -
A yearning I can never forget.
Were you here with me, Surissé,
could you understand
the dilemmas I am in.
I know that
in this world,
only you can understand me.
Only you can.
No one compares to you.
Your Majesty,
Dr. Wen asked me to present
this letter from the Palace of Pearl Jade.
Don't worry, My Lady.
The lives of my family
depend on whether His Majesty
agrees to see me or not.
My Lady, Mr. Su is here.
Your Highness,
His Majesty asks you to head over
to the Hall of Mental Cultivation.
One moment, Mr. Su.
I'll be ready right away.
Yes. I'll be waiting outside.
No need to bow when it's not convenient to.
Orchid told me that you‘ve been having
dreams in your sleep in your pregnancy.
Have you been sleeping better lately?
Has Your Majesty really seen
me having unsound sleep?
Did Your Majesty believe so
simply because Madam Orchid said so?
Instead of asking the doctors
if I was prescribed any calming medicine?
Or what I dreamed about?
What are you implying?
I just wanted to say that
judgments should not be made
based on only one person's story.
So, are you sleeping well recently?
The initial few months
were indeed restless.
But it's been slightly better now.
What Orchid said was true.
Madam Orchid has no intention to deceive Your Majesty.
But the officials in court
are constantly fighting for power.
Not all of them are truthful and impartial.
You requested to see me.
Instead of asking about me,
do you just to talk about this?
Have you repented for
your major disrespect to Empress Première?
Would Your Majesty believe me
if I say it was unintentional?
Whether it was intentional or not,
you made a grave mistake.
For my grave offence to Empress Première,
I'm willing to be confined for life,
forbidden to see Your Majesty.
But I beg of Your Majesty...
Please further investigate my father's case.
Don't let anyone be falsely accused.
As you said earlier,
I shouldn't solely rely on one-sided arguments.
I won't trust everything that Emin has to say.
However, regarding Qian Mingshi,
I've witnessed your father's words
and actions with my own eyes.
Based on all the facts,
this decision is not unfair to your family.
The circumstances can be changeful and deceptive.
I don't know what really happened.
Nevertheless, will Your Majesty not consider
my father's steadfast loyalty to Your Majesty?
Zhen Yuandao and his wife are advanced in age,
so I will grant them clemency.
I have given the order
to banish Zhen Yuandao and
his dependents to Ningguta.
They won't become the slaves
of the frontiersmen who surrendered.
They will just be living there.
With respect to his hard work.
Ningguta is bitterly cold.
My parents, at their age...
How can they survive such hardship!
Your Majesty...
Is there really ironclad evidence against my father?
Or is Your Majesty casting doubt on him
because you are possessed by the treachery
of State Prince Dun and Nian Gengyao?
Do you know what you are talking about?!
To my beloved wife Surissé:
My heart aches when I think of your tragic passing.
Leaving me behind in this sorrowful shell.
You lift my soul to see you in my dreams -
A yearning I can never forget.
Even though I have encountered
Sourire to your resemblance,
who temporarily eased my suffering.
After all, “The clouds are not the same
once you’ve passed Mountain Wushan.”
“The clouds are not the same
How nice of a comparison it is!
Did I gain all the favor...
solely because of Empress Première?
Because I resemble her?
So what am I?
What am I to you?
Now you know.
In fact,
it's your blessing
to look like Surissé.
Is that so?
Is it really a blessing
or rather, a sin?
Not only is Your Majesty mistaken,
I'm also at fault!
All these years,
the affection, and the time...
All spent on the wrong person!
Your Majesty.
What is it?
Spill it!
It was reported from jail
that Mr. Zhen contacted the plague.
His life is in critical condition.
Your Highness!
Your Highness is with child.
You have to take care of yourself!
Your Majesty ...
You Majesty's decision cannot be revoked.
But, my father is falsely accused.
I beg of Your Majesty.
Please save my father's life.
Don't let him die without justice.
I am willing to take responsibility for everything.
Understood.
Your Highness should leave.
Your Highness.
What happened?
Here.
The sedan is ready. We'll go quickly.
Is everything all right?
Your Highness, please take care.
Your Highness.
Be careful.
Quick, lift up the sedan.
Move. Quickly.
Lower the sedan.
My Lady.
My Lady...
My Lady! My Lady!
[Aspice]
Your Majesty, Concubine Sourire had serious bleeding.
Could be giving birth soon.
Her prenatal qi was damaged after
visiting the Hall of Mental Cultivation.
Looks like a premature birth.
Lunar, Lunar, hurry up.
Get the sedan ready.
I'm going to the Palace of Pearl Jade.
- Yes.
- Hurry.
Don't go right now.
I have to!
I must be there.
Giving birth is crucial to Huan'er.
Stop.
His Majesty needs to see for himself
how hard Sourire is protecting
this heir with her life.
This way, His Majesty will always
have Sourire on his mind.
It's her only chance to regain favor.
Why does she need this kind of favor?
Perhaps you don't need it,
but Sourire has no other choice.
If Sourire weren't able to save herself,
then the child also wouldn't be able to survive.
Then, I will bring His Majesty over.
My sister,
His Majesty has to bring himself over.
Otherwise, you will be pleading with him.
However, there's one thing that's more important.
If Sourire's father lost his life,
Sourire would still be the daughter of a
disgraced official even if she gives birth to a child.
How will she be able to lift her head in the palace?
All right.
I will go arrange
Dr. Wen to treat Sourire's father.
Your Highness, Push. Your Highness.
Your Highness. I can see half the head.
Push. Your Highness.
Your Highness. Push.
Push. I can see the head, Your Highness.
Push.
Keep going, Your Highness.
Your Highness. Push.
Your Majesty must not worry.
Don't worry.
Is somebody looking after
Zhen Yuandao in the jail?
Noble Lady has recommended Dr. Wen.
He has departed.
That's good.
Here. Here!
Your Majesty, a child has been delivered.
Congratulations to Your Majesty.
It's a princess.
Congratulations, Your Majesty.
A princess is good too.
A princess is good too!
I will go see Concubine Sourire.
Your Majesty, look at you!
This is not your first princess.
It's just a princess. Do I look happy at all?
Your Majesty, you cannot hide that smile.
It's all over your face.
Your Majesty.
Concubine Sourire gave birth to a princess.
A princess?
Brilliant.
Will His Majesty change his
heart because of this princess?
Even if Heaven's will is going to change,
Sourire will not accept it.
So beautiful.
Your Highness.
Congratulations, Your Highness.
You gave birth to a princess.
The princess is healthy.
She looks really beautiful too.
My Lady, you scared me to death.
You were unconscious for quite a while.
I will serve some tea for you.
Your Highness...
Here, bring the child over.
Let Her Highness see the princess.
Your Highness.
This is the princess's nursemaid.
The princess was born prematurely.
The doctor said that she needs
to be taken extra care of.
Your Highness, His Majesty is here.
His Majesty the Emperor.
Peace and grace to Your Majesty.
Grace to Your Majesty.
All rise. Rise.
I thank Your Majesty.
Concubine Sourire,
have you not thought it through?
What does Your Majesty want me to think through?
You have given birth to a princess for me.
Are you still going to act with emotions?
I have decided
not to vent anger on you,
regardless of the decision on your family.
If you wish,
I can issue a decree tomorrow
to grant you the rank of Consort.
I am a virtue less concubine.
I dare not shamefully hold the title of Consort.
Huan Huan ...
If you wish,
you’re still my beloved consort.
I’ll treat you just like before.
Just like before?
Your Majesty believes
we still can return to the former days?
I have indeed
pampered you excessively.
With a disposition like yours,
you're not suited to staying in the palace.
I thank Your Majesty.
Living in the temple will calm your heart.
You don’t need to live here now.
Right.
I have no more reasons to live here.
With a mother like me
who has such a woeful family,
the princess only has more to suffer.
Since I have decided to leave,
please allow me to give her a name.
I seek Your Majesty’s permission.
Yes.
I’ll name her ...
Rissé.
Rissé?
How dare I give her a reminiscent
name of the late Empress's?
It’s the character from “A strand of hair
tied to my husband's, binding my heart to his.”
What I failed to accomplish -
I hope the princess will be able to.
I will pray for her with an oil lamp by the Buddha
in the remnant of my life.
You don’t have to live in a
nunnery outside the palace.
You can stay at the Baohua Hall here.
No.
I'm a person of ill omen.
I dare not disturb the peace in the palace.
If so, leaving sooner will benefit you.
Don't stay any longer in the palace.
Your Highness.
My Lady.
I have but one more request.
Speak.
After my departure,
I hope the princess will be raised by
Her Highness Consort Estime.
If this is permitted,
I would have no more regret.
Consort Honnête has adopted Wenyi.
Consort Estime is able to commit.
Born in the dim moonlight...
I will grant the princess the
honorary name Longyue [misty moon].
Princesses are granted their honorary
names when they turn one month old.
Longyue is honored to be granted one shortly after birth.
I am thankful for Your Majesty's graciousness.
Anything else that you want to tell me?
"The broken red string of the zither;
The missing piece on a shattered mirror."
"The drying of morning dew;
The ending of spring blooms."
"The chant of Grey-Haired Lament;
The grief of parting’s sorrows."
"Generously feed yourself
and worry nothing about me."
"I bid to the roiling Jin River"
"an indefinite farewell for my husband.”
Very well.
Since it is so,
I have nothing else to say.
You are resolved to leave.
I and Consort Estime will raise Longyue well.
Your Highness.
My Lady.
Sourire, why are you doing this to yourself?
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
https://magpiebridgebrigade.cn
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Theme: The Phoenix Taking Flight
[phoenix is the symbol of an empress]
The dreams I dimly recall;
The past I hardly remember,
amidst the autumn moons and the spring flowers.
Like the moon's reflection on water
or flowers seen through mist - floating and drifting.
The joyous sounds you brought;
The silence you left;
Changing faster than clouds can turn to rain.
Our minds resonated;
Our hearts beat in unison;
But we lost what we once possessed.
A poem to converse;
A melody to accompany;
A heart to bind to mine.
I hoped for endless longing and eternal promise,
but I’m left with only the flute and the zither.
With affection, I pleased;
With my heart, I committed;
With my arms, I embraced.
I desired to be remembered;
Desired to be cherished;
Why am I only hated and deceived?
My wish ran against my will.
Behold the mockery of destiny and the game of fate.
My unwavering love is gone
like flowers swept away in the wind.
Praying for a bright moon;
Praying for a rising sun;
Dreaming to bask in the spring breezes.
But the unsparing northern winds carry snow and rain
to destroy the aspirations of the plum tree.
A phoenix about to take flight rustles its wings
but the arc of its flight is unseen.
The phoenix tree sways in the wind,
shedding memories in the whispers of the falling leaves.